<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article>
<article
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  lang="en">
  <info>
    <title>Clipboard Spec</title>

    <releaseinfo>1.0</releaseinfo>
    <pubdate>2000-12-01</pubdate>

    <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <firstname>Havoc</firstname>
      <surname>Pennington</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <address>
          <email>hp@redhat.com</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </info>
  <para>
    Historically, X clients have not handled cut-and-paste in a
    consistent way, leading users to believe that X doesn’t even have a
    working clipboard. This isn’t really accurate; there is a
    conventional behavior, somewhat standardized in the ICCCM. But many
    apps don’t follow the conventional behavior.
  </para>
  <para>
    X has a thing called <quote>selections</quote> which are just
    clipboards, essentially (implemented with an asynchronous protocol
    so you don’t actually copy data to them). There are three standard
    selections defined in the ICCCM: PRIMARY, SECONDARY, and CLIPBOARD.
  </para>
  <para>
    The ICCCM defines these as follows:
  </para>

  <blockquote>
    <literallayout>"The selection named by the atom PRIMARY is used for all com-
mands  that take only a single argument and is the principal
means of communication between clients that use  the  selec-
tion mechanism.

The selection named by the atom SECONDARY is used:

o   As  the second argument to commands taking two arguments
    (for example, "exchange  primary  and  secondary  selec-
    tions")

o   As  a  means  of  obtaining data when there is a primary
    selection and the user does not want to disturb it

The selection named by the atom CLIPBOARD is  used  to  hold
data  that  is  being  transferred between clients, that is,
data that usually is being cut and then pasted or copied and
then  pasted."</literallayout>
  </blockquote>

  <para>
    In addition, the ICCCM has a thing called <quote>cut buffers</quote>
    which most clients no longer support.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are two historical interpretations of the ICCCM:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        use PRIMARY for mouse selection, middle mouse button paste, and
        explicit cut/copy/paste menu items (Qt 2, GNU Emacs 20)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        use CLIPBOARD for the Windows-style cut/copy/paste menu items;
        use PRIMARY for the currently-selected text, even if it isn’t
        explicitly copied, and for middle-mouse-click (Netscape,
        Mozilla, XEmacs, some GTK+ apps)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    No one ever does anything interesting with SECONDARY as far as I can
    tell.
  </para>
  <para>
    The current consensus is that interpretation 2) is correct. Qt 3 and
    GNU Emacs 21 will use interpretation 2), changing the behavior of
    previous versions.
  </para>
  <para>
    The correct behavior can be summarized as follows: CLIPBOARD works
    just like the clipboard on Mac or Windows; it only changes on
    explicit cut/copy. PRIMARY is an <quote>easter egg</quote> for
    expert users, regular users can just ignore it; it’s normally
    pastable only via middle-mouse-click.
  </para>
  <para>
    The rationale for this behavior is mostly that behavior 1) has a lot
    of problems, namely:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        inconsistent with Mac/Windows
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        confusingly, selecting anything overwrites the clipboard
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        not efficient with a tool such as xclipboard
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        you should be able to select text, then paste the clipboard over
        it, but that doesn’t work if the selection and clipboard are the
        same
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the Copy menu item is useless and does nothing, which is
        confusing
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        if you think of PRIMARY as the current selection, Cut doesn’t
        make any sense since the selection simultaneously disappears and
        becomes the current selection
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Application authors should follow the following guidelines to get
    correct behavior:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        selecting but with no explicit copy should only set PRIMARY,
        never CLIPBOARD
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        middle mouse button should paste PRIMARY, never CLIPBOARD
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        explicit cut/copy commands (i.e. menu items, toolbar buttons)
        should always set CLIPBOARD to the currently-selected data (i.e.
        conceptually copy PRIMARY to CLIPBOARD)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        explicit cut/copy commands should always set both CLIPBOARD and
        PRIMARY, even when copying doesn’t involve a selection (e.g. a
        <quote>copy url</quote> -option which explicitly copies an url
        without the url being selected first)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        explicit paste commands should paste CLIPBOARD, not PRIMARY
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        a selection becoming unselected should never unset PRIMARY
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        possibly contradicting the ICCCM, clients don’t need to support
        SECONDARY, though if anyone can figure out what it’s good for
        they should feel free to use it for that
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        cut buffers are evil; they only support ASCII, they don’t work
        with many clients, and they require data to be copied to the X
        server. Therefore clients should avoid using cut buffers and use
        only selections.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Apps that follow these guidelines give users a simple mental model
    to understand what’s going on. PRIMARY is the current selection.
    Middle button pastes the current selection. CLIPBOARD is just like
    on Mac/Windows. You don’t have to know about PRIMARY if you’re a
    newbie.
  </para>
  <para>
    I don’t think there’s a sane mental model if we collapse everything
    into PRIMARY and ignore clipboard, see rationale above.
  </para>
  <para>
    A remaining somewhat odd thing about X selections is that exiting
    the app you did a cut/copy from removes the cut/copied data from the
    clipboard, since the selection protocol is asynchronous and requires
    the source app to provide the data at paste time. The solution here
    would be a standardized protocol for a <quote>clipboard
    daemon</quote> so that apps could hand off their data to a daemon
    when they exit. Or alternatively, you can run an application such as
    xclipboard which constantly <quote>harvests</quote> clipboard
    selections.
  </para>
  <para>
    References:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>the ICCCM, obviously</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/~keithp/talks/selection.ps">xfree86.org/~keithp/talks/selection.ps</ulink></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><ulink url="http://www.jwz.org/doc/x-cut-and-paste.html">jwz.org/doc/x-cut-and-paste.html</ulink></para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</article>
